Irving Fine Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Music (Box 1-4, Box 16)
  - Music by Others (Box 3, Box 16)
    - Salas, Juan Orrego
      - Canticos de Navidad, Ozalid 3-part vocal score; [4] p.; On cover: "To my good friend and colleague Irving Fine with best wishes, Juan Orrego Salas, 1952"; Contents: Villancico I Aleluya Villancico (Danza) (Box-folder 16/2)
    - Sapp, Allen
      - A maiden's complaint in spring-time: chamber cantata for women's voices and nine instruments (1959), Photocopy of holograph piano-vocal score; [30] p.; On cover: "To Irving Fine, from whom I learned how to be a musician and for whom my admiration has continued to grow" (Box-folder 16/3)
      - Trio No. 1, [for] piano, violin, and cello (1949), Ozalid holograph score; 37 p.; On cover: "To Irving in appreciation for everything, Allen" (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Shapero, Harold
      - Three amateur sonatas (1944), Ozalid holograph score for piano, annotated; 33 p.; On cover: "To Irving and Verna in real friendship from H. S., January 3, 1945" (Box-folder 16/4)
      - Variations in C minor, for piano (1947), Ozalid holograph score; 17 p.; At top: "To Igor Stravinsky"; On cover: "To Irving on his birthday, December 3, 1947, from Harold" (Box-folder 16/4)
    - Spies, Claudio
      - Descanso en jardรญn: tres cantos por los mรญos en Conchalรญ, [for] tenor, baritone, flute, oboe, clarinet, and bassoon (1957), Ozalid holograph score, annotated; [24] p.; On cover: "For Irving, in ancient friendship!, Claudio, 2.VI.1957" (Box-folder 16/5)
      - Recitativo and aria, for flute and piano (1946), Ozalid holograph score; 11 p.; On title page: "For Irving and Verna with my best wishes, Claudio, Cambridge, 7.X.1947" (Box-folder 16/5)
      - Sonata-allegro, for piano (1945), Ozalid holograph score; 9 p.; On title page: "For Irving with my gratitude, Claudio, 24.XI.1946" (Box-folder 16/5)
    - Talma, Louise
      - Alleluia in form of toccata, for piano. New York: Carl Fischer, Inc., 1947., On cover: "For Irving, with admiration and affection, Louise" (Box-folder 16/6)
      - String quartet 1954, Ozalid holograph score; 35 p.; On cover: "To dear Irving, from whom I learned how to write this quartet, Love Louise, November 17, 1954" (Box-folder 16/6)
    - Wernick, Richard
      - Trio, for clarinet, violin, and violoncello (1962), Ozalid copyist's score; 20 p.; On title page: "For my dear friend Verna Fine with much love, Dick, 3/23/63" (Box-folder 16/7)
- Writings (Box 5)
  The Writings series is arranged into two subseries: Writings by Irving Fine and Writings by Others. These subseries contain manuscript, typescript, and printed materials (published and unpublished), including lectures, program notes, and miscellany.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by author or title.
  - Writings by Irving Fine (Box-folder 5/1-14)
    - [Brandeis School of Creative Arts, 1955], Typescript, annotated; 6 p. (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Composer and his audience, 1956, Typescript; 11 p. (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Education for youth in the world of today and tomorrow, Typescript, annotated; 7 p. (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Elementary theory in the music curriculum at Harvard College, Typescript, annotated; 9 p. (2 copies) (Box-folder 5/4)
    - [French music, post-WWII (1951)] See: [Musique concrรจte]
    - [Milhaud, Darius, 1949], Typescript, annotated; 4 p. (Box-folder 5/5)
    - [Miscellaneous notes and musings], Ms.; 9 leaves (Box-folder 5/6)
    - [Musique concrรจte], Typescript, annotated; 3 p.; Includes reference materials; Includes: [French music, post-WWII (1951)]. Typescript, annotated, and ms. notes; 11 p. + [1] p. (Box-folder 5/7)
    - [Program notes], Tyescript/ms. materials, including a bio sketch; [14] p. (Box-folder 5/8)
    - The School of Creative Arts, 1952, Typescript copy; 2 p. (Box-folder 5/9)
    - The story of twentieth century music, 1940s, Typescript draft, annotated; [32] p.; Includes: typescript copy; 24 p.; Includes: photocopy of published version (Box-folder 5/10)
    - [Tanglewood, American music, 1947], Typescript/ms. materials, including notes, outlines, drafts; [59] p. total; Note: lectures at Tanglewood and Amherst College, 1947. (Box-folder 5/11)
    - [Tanglewood, Seminar in contemporary music, 1957], Typescript/ms.; [39] p.; Lectures: American Composer - Older Generation Neo Classicism (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Twelve poems of Emily Dickinson set to music by Aaron Copland, 1953, Typescript and ms. drafts; [9] p. (Box-folder 5/13)
    - What is the proper function of music criticism?, Typescript; 4 p. (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Writings by Others (Box-folder 5/15-18)
    - Burns, John Horne
      - Modo and the mortals. A play in one act, with music., Typescript copy; 25 p. (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Michigan, University of
      - Irving Fine: An American Genius, Typescript photocopy; 8 p.; Note: University of Michigan radio broadcast (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Pizer, Stephen M.
      - Irving Fine., Typescript copy; [21] p.; Includes leters (3) from Pizer to Irving Fine, 1962-1963.; Note: college paper (Box-folder 5/17)
    - Pollack, Howard
      - Irving Fine. (Box-folder 5/18)
- Correspondence, 1940-1992 (Box 6-7, Box-folder 13/10-11)
  The Correspondence series is arranged into two subseries. The first subseries, General Correspondence, consists of letters to Irving Fine (and Verna Fine). The second subseries, Business Correspondence, consists of papers and letters from 1962, 1988, and 1989.
  Arrangement of the General Correspondence subseries is alphabetically by name of correspondent. The second subseries, Business Correspondence, is arranged chronologically.
  - General Correspondence (Box 6-7)
    - Bernstein, Leonard, 1945-1991, Contents: Letters (photocopies) sent to Leonard Bernstein (1945-1962) (BOX: 6/1) Letters from Leonard Bernstein (1945-1991) (BOX: 6/2-3) (Box-folder 6/1-3)
    - Boosey & Hawkes, 1961 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Boulanger, Nadia, 1947-1970 (Box-folder 6/5)
    - Brandeis University, 1961-1967, Access point(s): A. L. Sachar (Box-folder 6/6)
    - Breuer, Robert, 1962 (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., 1966, Access point(s): Leonard Burkat (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Condolences, Note: re Irving Fine (Box-folder 6/9-10)
    - Copland, Aaron, 1944-1977, 1980, 1986, 1991, Contents: Copland, Aaron (1944-1950) (BOX: 6/11) Copland, Aaron (1951-1959) (BOX: 6/12) Copland, Aaron (1960-1977) (BOX: 6/13) Copland, Aaron (1980, 1986, 1991) (BOX: 6/14) Copland, Aaron (photocopies) (BOX: 6/15) (Box-folder 6/11-15)
    - Cummington School of the Arts, 1962, Access point(s): Harold Sproul (Box-folder 6/16)
    - Davis, Sylvia, [1962] (Box-folder 6/17)
    - Denny, William, 1962 (Box-folder 6/18)
    - Effron, Jesse, 1962, Note: typescript carbon of 1962 letter from Irving Fine to Jesse Effron. (Box-folder 6/19)
    - Fine, Claudia; Emily Fine, and Joanna Fine, Note: daughters of Irving Fine (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Fine, George (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Fine, Verna (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Foss, Lukas, 1948-1982 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - French, Richard, 1962 (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Friedman, Sidney, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Fromm, Herbert (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Fromm, Paul (Box-folder 7/8)
    - GC (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Ginastera, Alberto, 1946, 1954-1956 and Mercedes Ginastera (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Haieff, Alexei, 1946, 1987 and Sheila Haieff (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Harvard Crimson (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Heinsheimer, H. W. (Box-folder 7/13)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Box-folder 7/14)
    - Katz, Leonard William, 1944 and Barbara [Elaine] Fine, A.L.S. from Irving Fine, 1944 (Box-folder 7/15)
    - Kitto, H. D. F., 1964 (Box-folder 7/16)
    - Koussevitzky, Serge, 1946-1977 and Olga Koussevitzky (Box-folder 7/17)
    - Kraft, Victor, 1971 (Box-folder 7/18)
    - Kubik, Gail (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Lopatnikoff, Nikolai, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 7/20)
    - McCord, David, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Mennin, Peter, 1948 (Box-folder 7/22)
    - Milhaud, Darius (Box-folder 7/23)
    - The Nation (Box-folder 7/24)
    - Nicholas, E. Stanley (Box-folder 7/25)
    - Norman, Gertrude (Box-folder 7/26)
    - Pan American Union, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 7/27)
    - Persichetti, Vincent, 1960 (Box-folder 7/28)
    - Piston, Walter, 1963 (Box-folder 7/29)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1961, Note: A.L.S. from Irving Fine's secretary (Box-folder 7/30)
    - Rice, Philip M., 1962, Access point(s): Kansas State University (Box-folder 7/31)
    - Rochberg, George, 1956, Access point(s): Etude (Box-folder 7/32)
    - Rorem, Ned, 1983, 1992 (Box-folder 7/33)
    - Rudnick, Florence, 1941, Note: mother-in-law of Irving Fine; A.L.S. from Irving Fine, 1941 (Box-folder 7/34)
    - Schaeffer, Pierre, Access point(s): Groupe de recherches de musique concrรจte (Box-folder 7/35)
    - Schonberg, Harold C., 1963 (Box-folder 7/36)
    - Schuman, William, 1954-1957, 1962, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 7/37)
    - Shapero, Harold, 1948-1989 and Esther Shapero, Note: Esther Geller, artist (Box-folder 7/38)
    - Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1961 (Box-folder 7/39)
    - Smit, Leo, 1947-1991 (Box-folder 7/40)
    - Stravinsky, Igor, 1946-1971 (Box-folder 7/41)
    - Talma, Louise, 1963 (Box-folder 7/42)
    - Thomson, Virgil, 1959, 1968 (Box-folder 7/43)
    - Viereck, Peter, 1947 (Box-folder 7/44)
  - Business Correspondence (Box-folder 13/10-11)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 13/10)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 13/10)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 13/11)
- Photographs, 1937-1974 (Box 8)
  Photographs of Irving Fine and friends.
  Arranged according to subject.
  - Irving Fine, 1937-1962 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Irving Fine with others, 1945-1962 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Friends of Irving Fine, 1955-1974 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 1949-1966 (Box-folder 8/4)
- Programs, 1930-1992 (Box 9-12)
  Printed and typescript programs of music performances featuring the compositions of Irving Fine.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1930s (Box-folder 9/1)
  - 1940s (Box-folder 9/2)
  - 1950-1952 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - 1953-1956 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - 1957-1961 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 9/6)
  - 1962, Boston Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 9/7)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - 1964 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - 1965 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - 1970s (Box-folder 10/5)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - 1981-1982 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - 1986 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - 1987 January-April (Box-folder 11/4)
  - 1987 May-August (Box-folder 11/5)
  - 1987 September-December (Box-folder 11/6)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - 1989 January-June (Box-folder 12/2)
  - 1989 July-December (Box-folder 12/3)
  - 1990 January-June (Box-folder 12/4)
  - 1990 July-December (Box-folder 12/5)
  - 1991 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - 1992 (Box-folder 12/7)
- Clippings, 1940-1993 (Box 13)
  Primarily photocopies.
  - 1940s (Box-folder 13/1)
  - 1950s (Box-folder 13/2)
  - 1961-1962 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - 1963-1969 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - 1970s (Box-folder 13/6)
  - 1980-1983 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - 1983-1988 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - 1989-1993 (Box-folder 13/9)
- Scrapbooks, 1936-1962 (Box 17-21)
  Scrapbooks of Irving Fine.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1936-1949 (Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1949-1951 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1951-1953 (Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1953-1957 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1957-1960 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1960-1962 (Box 21)
- Printed Matter (Box 14)
  Miscellaneous printed materials.
  Arrangement is by subject.
  - Periodicals and miscellaneous printed material (Box 14)